[Music]
foreign
when you blew the whistle what was your
consideration and what happened to you
next
in 2002 we captured Abu zubeda at uh at
a safe house in faisalabad Pakistan
we believed at the time that Abu zubaida
was the third ranking person in Al Qaeda
that turned out to not be true although
he was a bad man
he was not the terrorist Mastermind that
we thought he was that was in March of
2002 in August of 2002 the CIA began
torturing him at a secret site and I
objected to it
I objected to it inside the CIA
I was told to mind my own business that
the decision had already been made there
was nothing anybody could do to stop it
or to change it and I should just move
on
but I knew that there were other people
inside the CIA who were making the same
complaints that I was and I expected
them I expected somebody to go public
that didn't happen a year and a half
later I resigned from the CIA
and went into the public sector I'm
sorry into the private sector and again
I I waited for somebody to come out and
say something
and that just never happened finally in
December of 2007
I got a call from an American journalist
quite a famous American journalist
who had questions about the torture of
Abu zubaida and I decided that I was
going to just
tell the truth
and go public
I actually probably naively did not
expect the Fallout
that resulted
but the most important part of that is
when I blew the whistle in December of
the bush FBI began investigating me
and they investigated me for a full year
from December of 2007 to December of
2008.
and then they decided that I had not
committed a crime and they closed the
investigation
then Barack Obama became president three
weeks later
and they secretly reopened the case
against me
and so they investigated me for three
more years
and then finally arrested me in 2012.
you wrote a letter to Snowden 10 years
ago when he made the Revelation you
suggested him what to do and wished him
best luck why did you do that did you
get any feedback from him
as soon as he made his Revelations I
realized how important he was
this was a huge story and we wouldn't
have known
that the government was spying on us
if Snowden hadn't told us
so I I wanted to write him a letter
because I knew
from that very moment
that he was going to go through exactly
the same experience that I was going
through and I didn't want him to make
the mistakes that I had made
so I wrote him actually two letters I
wrote him
a letter that was public and then I
wrote him a private letter
that a friend of ours delivered to him
and I told him to
embrace support wherever he could find
it especially on Capitol Hill
I told him to not trust anybody
anybody
because
everyone is
a potential FBI source
and I told him to hire the best lawyers
money could buy in fact I recommended
that he hire my lawyers which he did
in in most aspects it worked out well
for him to him I've talked to him many
times
uh you know he said something that was
very interesting he he was willing to go
to prison he was willing to come back
and face trial and go to prison he told
me he was willing to to serve 20 years
in prison
but what he wanted to do and this is
what the the lawyers were trying to
negotiate with the justice department
he wanted to be able to stand up in
court and explain why he did what he did
and the justice department said never
and he said then I won't come back
and so he didn't
how do you think of his whistleblowing
action what commonalities do you have
his his whistleblowing was absolutely
critical we had no idea that the that
NSA was spying on us we had no idea that
the FBI was using that information
without court orders or warrants to spy
on us so I think he's a bona fide hero I
think that the country owes him a great
debt of of thanks and gratitude for what
he did
to you and
um the last time I talked to him like
through Skype was three years ago
January it was right before covid
started and
um now it's through Twitter that's how
he does most of his communication
through Twitter direct messages he's an
intensely private person
um he doesn't think he did anything that
was particularly unusual he's wrong
about that of course
but he wants to be just a normal man
who's living his life with his wife and
his children that's that's really what
he wants he money's not important to him
and um
he just wants to get his truth out there
10 years on
CE Lakes brought in terms of you as
spying Behavior
around the world they've intensified
their behavior
you know we we've had Revelations now on
multiple occasions for example that this
that the NSA was intercepting Angela
merkel's cell phone okay that's that's
big news she was one of our closest
allies when the information was first
revealed
Hillary Clinton went to Germany and
apologized
and then we did it again
the problem there is if you look at
American public opinion most Americans
want the CIA and the NSA to spy on
foreign leaders even our friends
uh at the very least we we can learn
what they're intending to do in trade
negotiations at the very most
maybe it can disrupt some sort of an
attack you know if it's an unfriendly
country
so in terms of spying around the world
the American people love it and they
want more of it
in terms of spying domestically that is
very specifically illegal
these intelligence services are not
allowed to spy on Americans
and they do it anyway
and so what snowden's leaks have have
caused
and this is really not
enough
but what they've caused is Congress is
now watching more closely and exercising
better oversight